Boker Tov בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, happy Yom Yerushalayim יום ירושלים, Yom
Yerushalayim, 43rd day of the Omer עומר, Omer,
erev erev Rosh Chodesh ערב ערב ראש חודש. Erev Erev Rosh Chodesh.
Okay, we pick up today's Daf Chet דף ח, Daf Chet, we
pick up at the bottom of Daled Amud Bet ד עמוד ב,
Daled Amud Bet, about 10 lines from the bottom, Tani Rabbi Chiya
תני רבי חייא. Tani Rabbi Chiya. So we are now, we have
worked through the different explanations of the Mishna משנה, Mishna, Shor שור,
Shor, Bor בור, Bor, Ma'aveh מבעה, Ma'aveh, and Hev'er הבער. Hev'er. We've
discussed that if the Regel רגל, Regel, if an animal walking kicks
stones, it pays half because that's sort of a Kocho כוחו Kocho
plus it's incidental. We've discussed the idea that one way that you
can read the Mishna משנה Mishna that has Adam אדם Adam in
the Mishna משנה, Mishna, and that would maybe conceptualize that even by
a person who damages himself, it would be more because of negligence
than by the fact that they've done it, two ways of understanding
when why a person pays. Is it basically they did it, strict
liability or negligence? Similar type of a question about why the animal,
why you pay when your animals doing it. Okay, and now we
are listing Braisot ברייתות Braisot that add other things to the list
of Avot Nezikin אבות נזיקין. Avot Nezikin. So Rabbi Oshaya רבי אושעיא
Rabbi Oshaya expanded the list of types of cases where human beings
can cause damage, and he included first of all personal injury where
you have extra payment of suffering and of loss of labor and
of the hospital bills and etc. And he included cases of the
Shomrim שומרים Shomrim which don't directly cause damage, but through their negligence
or even if it's not negligence, like a Sho'el שואל, Sho'el, but
somehow they are liable for damage. Okay, but that's not through a
direct act. Okay, so that's one way of expanding the list from
four to thirteen. Now we have another expanded list, let's take a
look. So it's about again about 10 lines from the bottom,
Tani Rabbi Chiya תני רבי חייא Tani Rabbi Chiya by the asterisk,
beginning of a line, Tani Rabbi Chiya Esrim V'Arba Avot Nezikin תני
רבי חייא עשרים וארבעה אבות נזיקין. Tani Rabbi Chiya Esrim V'Arba Avot
Nezikin. Rabbi Chiya's Braisa ברייתא Braisa had 24 categories of Nezikin נזיקין.
Nezikin. Okay, so we had 13 before from Rabbi Oshaya רבי אושעיא
Rabbi Oshaya and now we're going to add 11 to that. So
let's see what 11 they are. Tashlumei Kefel תשלומי כפל, Tashlumei Kefel,
paying double in the case of burglary, Tashlumei Arba V'Chamisha תשלומי ארבעה
וחמישה, Tashlumei Arba V'Chamisha, four and five, if you, if it's a
burglary and then the animal is slaughtered or sold, if it's by
an animal, a Shor V'Seh
שור ושה, Shor V'Seh, right? Shor V'Seh שור ושה, Shor V'Seh, right,
exactly, an ox or a sheep. Haganav V'Hagazlan הגנב והגזלן, Haganav V'Hagazlan,
burglary which would be the principal, not the double, or Gazlan גזלן
Gazlan or such, which would also be the principal, so we're up
to four extra ones. Eidim Zomemim עדים זוממים, Eidim Zomemim, false witnesses
that are then found to have been in collusion or whatever. So
that's five. If they testify about money, they pay money. V'HaOnes V'HaMifateh
U'Motzi Shem Ra והאונס והמפתה ומוציא
שם רע, V'HaOnes V'HaMifateh U'Motzi Shem Ra, the rapist, the seducer, and
the one who libels his wife for not being a virgin, for
having committed adultery, for having committed adultery. So we're up to eight.
V'HaMetameh V'HaMedameh V'HaMenasach והמטמא והמדמע והמנסך, V'HaMetameh V'HaMedameh V'HaMenasach, which are really
three that normally are part of a Rabbinic Braisa ברייתא, Braisa, they're
not in a Mishna משנה, Mishna, they're not in a Pasuk פסוק,
Pasuk, so they're not Avot Nezikin אבות נזיקין. Avot Nezikin. These three
are the first that are not in the Psukim פסוקים Psukim and
yet they're being called Avot Nezikin אבות נזיקין Avot Nezikin because it's
like a classic case of Tannaitic teaching that somebody who makes a
person's grain Tameh טמא, Tameh, the Terumah תרומה Terumah Tameh טמא, Tameh,
right, or who mixes it up with, who mixes Terumah תרומה Terumah
and Chullin חולין Chullin together, or pours somebody's wine to Avoda Zara
עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. All now this stuff becomes either worthless or
worth less, haha.
Anyway, but you like that, huh? Anyway, but it's not visible, it
says Hezeik She'eino Nikkar היזק שאינו ניכר. Hezeik She'eino Nikkar. Okay, so
you really could call that one and it's really not in the
Psukim פסוקים, Psukim, but we're going to call it three which now
gets us an additional 11 for a total for an additional 11,
which makes us up now to 24. Okay, V'Hani Tlataysar והני תלת
סרי V'Hani Tlataysar plus the thirteen that we have, HaEsrim V'Arba העשרים
וארבעה, HaEsrim V'Arba, it's 24. Okay. So now we're going to ask
why did the previous list not include this? If we're looking to
expand, in what way conceptually has this list even broadened itself from
the previous list? Rabbi Oshaya Mai Ta'ama Lo Tani Hani רבי אושעיא
מאי טעמא לא תני הני? Rabbi Oshaya Mai Ta'ama Lo Tani Hani?
So why did Rabbi Oshaya רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya not teach this
whole list? Because he got us up to 13, why not add
these? Bemamona Ka'mar Uveknasa Lo Ka'mar בממונא קאמר ובקנסא לא קאמר. Bemamona
Ka'mar Uveknasa Lo Ka'mar. Because many of the things on this list
are not compensation, they're not Mamon ממון, Mamon, they're Knas קנס, Knas,
they're fines. So yes, they're monetary payments you make but they're not
compensatory. And therefore he was only interested in the types of compensatory
payments. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says now not everything on this
list, so we're going to look at the ones that are not
Knas קנס. Knas. The Gemara גמרא Gemara says Ganav V'Gazlan Demamona Hu
גנב וגזלן דממונא הוא? Ganav V'Gazlan Demamona Hu? How about a burglary
when you're paying just the principal? Let's say you admitted that you
were a burglar so you don't pay the Kefel כפל, Kefel, or
a Gazlan גזלן Gazlan where you always only pay the principal, that's
compensation, Lisni ליתני, Lisni, why not list it? Haktani Ley Shomer Chinam
Vehashoel הא קתני ליה שומר חינם והשואל. Haktani Ley Shomer Chinam Vehashoel.
No, because he already listed the Shomrim שומרים. Shomrim. Now really, Shomer
שומר Shomer and a Ganav גנב Ganav is not the same. So
what you have to understand here is the Rabbinic principle that if
you consciously swear falsely as a Shomer שומר Shomer and you say,
'Oh, the stuff got stolen, the stuff got burgled,' okay, and it
was Nignav נגנב, Nignav, it was Nigzal נגזל, Nigzal, you take an
oath, then you are treated like a Ganav גנב Ganav and a
Gazlan גזלן. Gazlan. Now by Gazlan גזלן Gazlan it's not such a
big Nafka Mina נפקא מינה, Nafka Mina, but it is a Nafka
Mina נפקא מינה Nafka Mina by a Ganav גנב Ganav because then
you would actually pay double, okay, if you claimed and took an
oath that it was
stolen. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says: רבי חייא נמי התנא ליה שומר חינם והשואל.
Rabbi Chiya nami hatana lei shomer chinam vehashoel. How about רבי חייא?
Rabbi Chiya? Don't you admit that this list of שומרים shomrim conceptually
would include a גנב ganav and גזלן gazlan type of a case?
No, תנא ממונא דאתי לידיה בהיתר וקתני ממונא דאתי לידיה באיסור. tana
mamona d'atei liyadei b'heter ukatani mamona d'atei liyadei b'issur. Now, he teaches
both a case of money that initially came into your possession legitimately;
you were given it to watch, and then you turned into a
גנב ganav and a גזלן gazlan by taking a false oath. And
then he conceptually separate, which he's completely right, it is conceptually quite
different, is when you actually initially took possession of
it in transgression, when you actually never had a legitimate right to
have it and you stole it from the outset. Actually, what you'll
even say is that conceptually you need the category of גנב ganav
and גזלן gazlan and then you could say the שומרים shomrim sometimes
become a גנב ganav and גזלן, gazlan, but you want to create
those as a conceptually distinct category. Okay, so that explains that, and
again, a lot of the other things are קנס. knass. How about
עדים זוממים? eidim zomemim? Is that a קנס? knass? עדים זוממים ממונא
הוא. eidim zomemim mamona hu. Wait one minute, עדים זוממים eidim zomemim
is money? It's—you're not paying more. Now, you might stop and say,
"Whoa, wait a minute." Now, this is a very—gets to an interesting
question, which we're going to be dealing with within significant sections of
this מסכת. masechet. What is the line between compensation and קנס, knass,
between ממונא mamona and קנס? knass? So the most—so let's look at
רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi says: עדים זוממים ממונא הוא. eidim zomemim mamona
hu. דכל דמשלם יותר מה שהזיק—if dechol d'meshaleim yoser ma shehizik you
ever pay beyond the damage, more than the damage, that's by definition
a
קנס. knass. כגון כפל ותשלומי ד' וה'—if kegon kefel vetashlumei daled ve'hei
you're paying more than the actual damage that you caused, the extra
you're paying is clearly a קנס. knass. קרי קנס כדלקמן. kari knass
k'dilkaman. וכגון—now ukegon another thing that could be a קנס knass is
כל דבר קצוב האמור בתורה. kol davar katzuv hamur batora. If it
is in payment for damage, but it is not—it is not proportionate
or it is not, you know, a function of the cost of
the amount of damage caused, but it's a fixed amount. So if
you're paying a fixed amount, even if it is in compensation for
damage, the fact that it's fixed means it's not really compensation; it's
somewhat symbolic, it's somewhat arbitrary.
כגון חמישים דאונס ומפתה. kegon chamishim d'ones umefateh. Okay, now actually the
חמישים דאונס ומפתה chamishim d'ones umefateh is not a good
example, ומוציא שם רע. umotzi shem ra. It's funny that רש"י Rashi
gives that.
כולהו הוי קנסא. kulu havei knasa. All of those actually are also
more than the damage. There's a payment for damages in the case
of seduction; in the case of מוציא שם רע, motzi shem ra,
there were no damages—I mean, I guess you could say damage to
reputation. Okay, but a better example would have even been a case
of—thank you—would have been a case of the thirty that you pay
when your ox gores a slave. Okay, because there there really is
a loss of property, as it were—I mean, obviously a loss of
life—okay, and rather than assessing how much was your slave worth, you
pay a fixed amount of thirty—thirty שקל, shekel, of thirty כסף. kessef.
So a way to determine whether it's קנס knass is: is it
a payment beyond compensation or when there is no loss and you're
still paying something? Or even if there is a loss, but you're
not paying equivalent to the loss, you're paying a fixed amount. Those
are ways to say it's not real compensation. רש"י Rashi is laying
that out to explain to you why עדים זוממים eidim zomemim is
presumed to be ממונא. mamona. Because by עדים זוממים, eidim zomemim, okay,
there's a loss, you're paying equivalent to the loss, that's ממונא. mamona.
But somebody might say, "Wait one minute." Right? I mean, maybe that's
the paradigmatic case of equivalent, כאשר זמם ולא כאשר עשה, ka'asher zamam
v'lo ka'asher asa, it's exactly equal. But somebody could say, "Wait a
minute, עדים זוממים eidim zomemim can't be תשלומין. tashlumin. You know why
עדים זוממים eidim zomemim can't be תשלומין?" tashlumin? Michael, tell us why
עדים זוממים eidim zomemim can't be—כאשר
זמם ולא כאשר עשה לאחיו, ka'asher zamam v'lo ka'asher asa l'achiv, it
doesn't sound like it could—first of all, it could be anything, you
know.
Okay, no, but when it is with ממונא, mamona, why is it
not תשלומין? tashlumin?
What if it's a
קנס?
knass? Well, right, if עדים זוממים eidim zomemim admitted, are they off?
But that actually raises the question. No, but the more immediate thing
to say is is that the normal principle is כאשר זמם ולא
כאשר עשה, ka'asher zamam v'lo ka'asher asa, that they only get punished
if they were plotting, not if they actually succeeded. So therefore, if
they were plotting to do it, then there was no actual loss.
So how could you call it ממונא mamona if there was no
actual loss? Which might be where רש"י Rashi is trying to say,
"Well, okay, but it's still ממונא mamona because it's still equivalent to—it's
not arbitrary, it's not more than the loss," okay, which is a
little funny. But would you call that ממונא mamona if it's for
a loss they were attempting to cause without there being actual loss?
The גמרא Gemara sounds like it's prepared to say that. But look
at an important תוספות Tosafot on דף ד' עמוד ב'. daf daled
amud bet. תוספות Tosafot says: ועדים זוממים, ve'eidim zomemim, פירוש ריב"א, perush
Riva, דאפילו שילם על פי עדים זוממים חייבין. de'afilu shillem al pi
eidim zomemim chayavin. By עדים זוממים, eidim zomemim, we would have you
pay not only if they did not succeed, but by when it
came to monetary issues, the עדים זוממים eidim zomemim would pay even
if they did succeed in making the guy pay. Okay, well, let's
take a look. Okay, דלא שייך בממונא כאשר זמם ולא כאשר עשה
דאפשר בחזרה. delo shayach b'mamona ka'asher zamam v'lo ka'asher asa d'efshar b'hazara.
It's never really כאשר זמם ולא כאשר עשה ka'asher zamam v'lo ka'asher
asa because— It's never really done what they've done, because you could
always just reverse the judgment and the money could go back. So
you're always sort of in the כאשר זמם, ka'asher zamam, it's never
כאשר עשה ka'asher asah in a final way. The court ruled you
owe me $100 based on the testimony of עדים זוממים. edim zomemim.
It wasn't final what they did because the court could always tell
me to pay the money back, that it was a mistake. Okay,
so it's never a full כאשר עשה. ka'asher asah. They can't remove
the מלקות malkos that I got. Okay, they can't reverse the, what?
But in other cases of קנס knas with the... well.
All right, anyway, that's one explanation.
Okay, וריבא מפרש דלא צריך להאי טעמא. veRiva mefareish delo tzarich lehai
ta'ama. You don't even need the ריבא'ס Riva's explanation that it's not
a full כאשר עשה. ka'asher asah. דגבי ממון מחייבינן ליה בקל וחומר.
degabei mamon mechayavinan lei bekal vachomer. Why do we say by עדים
זוממים edim zomemim it's כאשר זמם ולא כאשר עשה? ka'asher zamam velo
ka'asher asah? Because the תורה Torah says כאשר זמם. ka'asher zamam. And
even though it's a קל וחומר kal vachomer to say they should
be punished when they only plotted, surely they should be punished when
they succeeded. But the answer is, no, but you can't punish somebody
based on a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Ah, but by monetary compensation,
you can punish somebody based on a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Okay?
דגבי ממון עונשין מן הדין. degabei mamon onshin min hadin. Okay? And
then he goes on with that. So it's an actually interesting issue
that תוספות Tosafos needs to say that because the גמרא Gemara thinks
עדים זוממים edim zomemim is ממון, mamon, needs to say that עדים
זוממים edim zomemim are paying when they succeeded, not just by monetary
issues, not just when they plotted. Because if they're only paying when
they plotted, then it would be קנס. knas. Okay, so this becomes
a very interesting question of how do you define ממון? mamon? So
by עדים זוממים edim zomemim you have an amount equivalent to the
damage, but for תוספות Tosafos it's not enough to say it's equivalent
and not arbitrary, you have to say there actually was loss and
damage, or else it also wouldn't be ממון. mamon. All right.
But the other condition that doesn't include עדים זוממים edim zomemim would
say that if they were successful...
Let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay? ועדים
זוממים דממונא הוא ליחשיב, ve'edim zomemim demamona hu lichshiv, but all that
was to explain why the גמרא Gemara thinks it's ממון mamon and
not קנס. knas. So סבר לה כרבי עקיבא, savar lah kerabi akiva,
he holds like רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, דאמר אין משלמין על פי
עצמן. de'amar ein meshalmin al pi atzman. Ah, just like what was
said, according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, he says that it is
קנס. knas. That if they admit that they were עדים זוממים, edim
zomemim, even in a monetary issue, they would not pay. אי סבר
לה כרבי עקיבא, ei savar lah kerabi akiva, so that's why because
there's an opinion that it actually is קנס knas and that's why
it's in רבי חייא'ס Rabbi Chiya's list and not in רבי אושעיא'ס
Rabbi Oshaya's list because רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya was not dealing with
קנס. knas. One minute. I'm sorry, did I get that right? Yeah,
I got that right. So yeah, because they're of the opinion that
it's קנס. knas. אי סבר לה כרבי עקיבא, ei savar lah kerabi
akiva, now wait a minute, you can't say that we're talking within
the mindset of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and עדים זוממים edim zomemim
is in the קנס knas column, because if that's true, וליתני תרי
גווני שור, velitni terei gavnei shor, we have another אב av that
you should list. Two types of a שור. shor. What are two
types of a
שור? shor? ליתני שור דהזיק שור וליתני שור דהזיק אדם. litni shor
dehizik shor velitni shor dehizik adam. A שור shor that gores a
שור shor and a שור shor that gores a person. Because we
just discussed the other day that even if an animal gores a
human being, the payment is just straight damages. It's not hospital bills,
it's not whatever. But רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva disagrees. דתנן רבי עקיבא
אומר אף תם שחבל באדם. detnan rabi akiva omer af tam shechaval
be'adam. Even if
a תם tam actually, excuse me, I said that wrong. We are...
you would not pay the extra type of personal injuries, but רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says that if a שור shor gores a person,
even though there would be no personal injury payments, you would only
pay for the loss, but it would not be half payment. The
idea that an ox only pays half the first three times is
only when it gores property. But when it gores a human, it
pays full.
אף תם שחבל באדם.
af tam shechaval
be'adam. Meaning just נזק, nezek, meaning just נזק. nezek.
Correct. Depreciation in the slave market, right?
Exactly. Okay, so you would just pay how damages but not hospital
bills, not pain, suffering, etc., but it would not be half. Okay?
אף תם שחבל באדם. af tam shechaval be'adam. If a תם tam
ox gores a human, משלם במותר נזק שלם. meshalem bemotar nezek shalem.
You pay in the balance, excuse me, the full amount. What does
the balance mean? So the case in the משנה Mishna over there
was that an ox and a person got into a fight. Okay?
So the person did damage to the ox, and the ox did
damage to the person. So you figure out whose damage was more
if the person did more and then and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says, so what you really should say is, if you pay half
by the ox, you figure out each column of damage. The human
pays full damages for the to the owner of the ox and
the owner of the ox pays half damages to the owner of
the person. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says no, you figure out the
difference and if the difference is there were more damages to the
person, then the owner of the ox pays full. Okay? So that's
just a special case, but what's really relevant is he says if
an ox gores a person, it's not half damages, it's full damages.
So then we should have had a different type of an ox.
Let's get the numbers up to 25. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, we didn't list that idea even though we're working within רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, because התם רבי עקיבא לגזיזיה. hatam rabi akiva legaziziah.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva sort of, you know,
broke his,
his, his, like, you know,
what...
They blunted, yeah, okay, they blunted his argument is what they said
or they he's already blunted
the force of his ruling. Right. Anyway, so he, you know, he's
already blunted his, that's a good, that's a good word.
I think it's
גזיזי, gzizei, that's what I was looking up, that the גזיזי gzizei
means something like
his what?
רש"י Rashi says the כח אגרופו. koach egrofo.
Yeah, his fist, his fist, right, thank you. Right.
So he so he thought maybe it's from a Greek word for
razor.
A Greek word meaning razor? No, רמח. romach.
רמח romach is a spear, a dagger. Okay, good, he blunted his
dagger. Okay, how did he blunt his dagger? דתניא, Datanya, רבי עקיבא
אומר, Rabbi Akiva Omer, יכול אף תם שחבל באדם ישלם מן העליה.
Yachol af tam shechaval be'adam yeshallem min ha'aliyah.
Now that I said that he pays full, maybe he pays full
when he damages a person even from like cash and not just
from the body of the animal. Let's say the full payments would
exceed the cost of the ox itself, would you pay even that?
תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, יעשה לו, ya'aseh lo, you shall do to
him מגופו migufo משלם ואינו
משלם
מן העליה. meshallem ve'eino meshallem min ha'aliyah. So you only pay from
the actual body of the ox, even when it's paying for damaging
a human and even when it's full payments, and you don't pay
from other types of property. Does everyone agree? Well, only well,
everyone else doesn't have to agree because everybody else disagrees with רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva since it's only half. So of course it's only
half that's from the body of the animal. But רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva is saying that the whole basic idea of paying half by
a goring ox is from the body of the animal. But רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is saying even though I'm saying full, it's limited
still to the cost of the body of the animal. It won't
be from general, from you know, from your general assets.
Now, the body of the animal, what do you mean?
If the animal is worth a thousand, no, if the animal's worth,
I mean we're going to I'm sort of being vague because we're
going to get to it, but if the animal's worth a thousand
dollars and gores a person and causes nine hundred dollars of damage,
according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, okay, then I now am a
nine-tenths owner in your ox. Okay, if it causes a thousand dollars
of damage, I'm a full owner of your ox. If it causes
twelve hundred dollars of damage, I'm a full owner of your ox
but you do not pay me the extra two hundred dollars. Okay,
so it's limited to the cost of the body of the animal
and actually the way it happens is I become a owner in
the animal for that amount. All right. So because it's not a
full payment of full damages, we didn't list it. Now תוספות Tosafot
says, now תוספות Tosafot says I don't care that it's not full,
it's still different than the other תם. tam. One is half and
one is the full amount limited to the cost of the body
of the animal, but why isn't it still listed as a separate
category? So we're going to see in a few minutes that the
lists of these categories, the reason they're listed is to tell you
that the payment comes from the best of the property. Okay, that's
why they're all being put into this into one big, you know,
list. And therefore תוספות Tosafot says is, so that's where that's why
this wasn't included, because this would be a type of payment that
does not come from the best of the property, it only comes
from the body of the animal. Okay, so we're within רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, עדים זוממים edim zomemim is קנס. knas. That's why it's
in רבי חייא's Rabbi Chiya list and not רבי אושעיא's Rabbi Oshaya
list. And even though according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva there's another
category of an ox that gores a person and pays full, since
that is not a standard full payment, it's only from the body
of the animal, we are not going to put it in, we're
not going to have it as a separate category.
Yeah, I understand these days that you know, we don't do עונשין
onshin anymore because we don't do קנסות knasot anymore, right? But what
do we do these days like about נזק, nezek,
you know, like the famous case of Travis the?
We're going to get to all of it. What do we do?
Okay, we're going to get to it, we have a whole מסכת
Masechet in front of us. There's going to be a definite addressing
of that question. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay.
Now, moving on.
והאונס והמפתה והמוציא שם רע, Veha'ones vehamifateh vehamotzi shem ra, how about
those? Now, you know, rape, seduction, and libel. Now, דממונא הוא, demamona
hu, that's ממון. mamon. Now, מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra is
not ממון, mamon, that was libel. I mean, again, you could say
that you're paying for defamation of character, but it's interesting, in general
if when it's not the specific case in the תורה Torah by
the husband accusing his bride of having committed adultery, we don't normally
have payments for defamation of character, which is an interesting issue. Okay,
so that's considered a קנס. knas. So that was just thrown in
because it's part of the list. But אונס ones and מפתה, mifateh,
the rape and the seduction, that is a that's considered that is
a ממון. mamon. One of the payments there is, I mean it's
hard to understand in the case of מפתה, mifateh, but in the
case of rape anyway, the you know, also how do you figure
out what it means that now this you know girl was raped?
What does that mean in terms of affecting her value on what
is it, the slave market, the bride market? We'll get to all
of those. Actually, a lot of that was in כתובות. Ketubot. But
anyway, but there is a payment there that is considered a ממון
mamon payment. So why wasn't that included in in the earlier lists
that either you know in the list of רבי אושעיא? Rabbi Oshaya?
So the גמרא Gemara says, ליתני, litni, no, so the גמרא Gemara
says look, ממה נפשך, mamma nafshach, אי נזק תנא ליה, i nezek
tana lei, because any type of payment of these cases is going
to be one of the personal injury payments. If we're talking about
the payment by the case of אונס ones and מפתה mifateh of
נזק, nezek, of damages, so רבי אושעיא's Rabbi Oshaya list had personal
injury and listed damages. אי צער. i tza'ar. What about the suffering?
תנא ליה. tana lei. That was also in Rabbi Oshaya's list. אי
בושת, ei boshet, תנא ליה. tana lei. It was בושת, boshet, that
was also in his list, meaning all the payments here that are
not קנס knas payments are personal injury payments. And Rabbi Oshaya's list
had personal injury. אי פגם, ei pagam, if it's what we call
the פגם, pagam, sort of like, you know, would be the way,
the stigma or something. So yeah, no, but anyway, היינו נזק, hainu
nezek, that we can, that's considered to be נזק. nezek. We worry
about all that when we get to אונס ומפתה. oness u-mifateh. מה
אית לך למימר, mah it lach lemeimar, what is the only thing
about אונס ומפתה oness u-mifateh that's not part of personal injury? קנסא,
knasa, the fine that you pay. בקינסא לא קמיירי, be-knasa lo ka-meiri,
we've already got through saying that we're not talking about the fine.
So the אונס מפתה ומוציא שם רע, oness mifateh u-motzi shem ra,
a major element of that of אונס ומפתה oness u-mifateh is personal
injury, that was in Rabbi Oshaya's list. Rabbi Hiyya was adding them
because there was also a fine associated with them. Rabbi Hiyya is
adding קנס, knas, Rabbi Oshaya is not dealing with קנס. knas. Okay,
last part of the list, okay, המטמא והמדמע והמנסך. ha-metameh ve-ha-medama ve-ha-menasech.
Okay, making your grain טמא tamei or mixing תרומה terumah with חולין
chullin or pouring the wine, those are cases of damages but not
visible damages. But it is damages. דממונא הוא וליתני, de-mamona hu ve-litni,
so that's standard monetary compensation. So why wasn't it in Rabbi Oshaya's
list? מה נפשך, mah nafshach, let's just make up your mind. אי
היזק שאינו ניכר שמיה היזק, ei hezek she-eino nikar shemeih hezek, if
we consider that type of damage to be a form of classic
damages even though it's not visible, התנא ליה נזק. ha-tana lei nezek.
So we've already dealt with when a human damages somebody's property. אי
היזק שאינו ניכר לא שמיה היזק, ei hezek she-eino nikar lo shemeih
hezek, if it's not considered real damages and it's only the Rabbis
make you pay, and it's really only a type of a fine
but it's not real, it's certainly not biblical payment of damages, so
then הוי ליה קנסא, havei lei knasa, it's a type of a
fine, וקנסא לא קמיירי, ve-knasa lo ka-meiri, and we're not dealing with
fines. So either that's just a different example of damages, or it's
a payment that's not about damages, it's a type of a קנס
knas and we're only dealing with ממון. mamon. So that's why it
wasn't in Rabbi Oshaya's list but it is in Rabbi Hiyya's list.
Now the גמרא's Gemara going to focus on, wait, why is it
in Rabbi Hiyya's list? לימא, leima, let us say, קסבר רבי חייא
היזק שאינו ניכר לא שמיה היזק. kasavar Rebbi Chiyya hezek she-eino nikar
lo shemeih hezek. He must hold that this isn't real damages, that
it's a fine, and that's why he had this as extra categories.
דאי שמיה היזק, de-ei shemeih hezek, if it was a real example
of just standard damages, התנא ליה נזק, ha-tana lei nezek, you already
have נזק. nezek. So why does Rabbi Hiyya have these as separate
categories? Why does he list them separately unless he's telling us that
this isn't classic נזק, nezek, that this is actually a type of
a fine? So the גמרא Gemara says no, not necessarily, it could
be a type of a נזק, nezek, but nevertheless it's important to
list them separately.
תנא היזקא דמינכר ותנא היזקא דלא מינכר. tana hezeka de-minchar ve-tana hezeka
de-lo minchar. He wanted to tell you this classic נזק nezek when
it's visible, and there's non-visible נזק. nezek. Yes, the הלכה halachah is
that that's a type of a נזק nezek and it's paying because
you pay for מזיק, mazik, but it's important to identify this as
another type of damages just so it should be clear that you
pay for this case as well. It's sort of like the גמרא
Gemara before about אי נמי, ei nami, no, אי נמי. ei nami.
He doesn't have to say it's לא שמיה היזק, lo shemeih hezek,
he could say it's שמיה היזק, shemeih hezek, but he just wants
to distinguish between two types of נזק nezek even though both of
them are נזק. nezek. Like the גמרא Gemara said before by שומר
shomer and a גנב. ganav. A שומר shomer could be a type
of a גנב, ganav, but we want to distinguish between two types
of a גנב. ganav.
היזק שאינו ניכר, hezek she-eino nikar, but it's שמיה היזק.
shemeih hezek. Right. Okay.
But the question's also, go ahead, listing it because these are examples
in the תורה? Torah? Right.
Well, it's not trying
to, no, first of all these aren't examples in the תורה, Torah,
only examples in חז״ל. Chazal. But I agree with you that what
the גמרא Gemara is saying is like he wants to deal with
like the classic.
More with conceptual categories?
Yeah, but then what are you going to do? Let's just list
every single משנה Mishnah in our מסכת masechet as one of the
אבות נזיקין, avot nezikin, right? You have to say there's some way
in which it's distinct. But yes, but anyway,
but yes, that's what we're doing. We're trying to cover all the
types of cases.
היזק שאינו ניכר.
hezek she-eino nikar.
Let's say there's less of it, and then some of it is
ניכר. nichar. I can't see this, what's left that is damaged. If
I started with a gallon of oil and poured out half of
it or whatever.
So the part that is ניכר, nichar, but the other part is
not ניכר. nichar.
That's what they're saying. Yeah, that we don't pay for unrecognized damages
to property.
But we do pay, right,
we don't pay it for character defamation. Correct. Even though that's unrecognized.
Yeah, but that's a good point. I mean, why don't you call
that היזק שאינו ניכר? hezek she-eino nikar?
Yeah, I mean, the difference is that in one case it makes
the object worth less, and in the other case it doesn't make,
I mean, you know, it doesn't make you, yeah, the way we
figure out damage is like you as a slave, you know, it's
a funny, it's an interesting,
it's an interesting thought. That's an interesting thought. Yeah, I mean, it's
a good question about why, how הלכה halachah does not have, you
have איסורא issura about being מוציא שם רע, motzi shem ra, you
have a classic example about מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra and
we never sort of abstracted it to create, it's an interesting way
of thinking about it, a type of a היזק שאינו ניכר, hezek
she-eino nikar, especially if it directly affects your livelihood. It's interesting. Yeah,
I have to think about that one. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Now, מניינא, minyana, okay, now בשלמא bishlama where are
we? Don't take it from
me. בשלמא לדתנא דידן, bishlama letana didan, our תנא tanna the author
of our משנה mishnah that only had four, so תנא מניינא tana
minyana he said four למעוטי דרבי אושעיא lemute deRabbi Oshaya because he
was not meaning it's not that he disagrees with anything on רבי
אושעיא's Rabbi Oshaya's list but conceptually he wants to talk about a
very narrowly defined list, ממון המזיק, mamon hamazik, right, and or if
it includes אדם adam only direct damages, so he wants to say
four to say I'm not dealing with these expanded lists conceptually I'm
dealing with a small list. Okay, רבי אושעיא, Rabbi Oshaya, when רבי
אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya said thirteen, okay, תנא מניינא tana minyana he gave
a number למעוטי דרבי חייא lemute deRabbi Hiyya because he also was
dealing with a more limited expanded list not the largest list possible,
he wasn't dealing with קנס, knas, he was only dealing with ממון,
mamon, and that's why he said thirteen to tell you and not
the bigger list of רבי חייא. Rabbi Hiyya. Again, nobody argues on
the הלכה halacha just conceptually what is outside of your list that
you have decided you don't want you're not including in your list.
So אלא מניינא דרבי חייא, ela minyana deRabbi Hiyya, אלא מניינא
דרבי חייא ela minyana deRabbi Hiyya למעוטי מאי? lemute mai? But when
רבי חייא Rabbi Hiyya says twenty-four, what's he coming to say is
not on his list? Now you could just say maybe everything is
on his list, he just wants you to remember that there are
twenty-four of them, it's a way of remembering because I get all
of them, one minute and you count, right? But the גמרא Gemara
assumes that if there's a number it means that something isn't included.
Okay, so that seems to be a pretty comprehensive list, what's not
included? So the גמרא Gemara says למעוטי מוסר ומפגל. lemute moser umefagel.
Okay, here's another case about where your words cause damage and you
don't pay. Okay, you hand over you're an informer to the government
about somebody who hasn't paid their taxes or whatever it is and
the government comes and they seize his property. Alright, so that's just
your words, that causes real damage. Okay, and המפגל hamefagel is your
כהן kohen who's thinking when it's שחיטה shechting an animal that you're
going to eat it at the wrong time or the wrong place
and you make the animal worthless. ולתני? uletni? So why not say
that? בשלמא מפגל bishlama mefagel I understand why you don't have the
case of פיגול pigul בקדשים לא קא מיירי. bekodashim lo ka mairi.
We're not dealing with קדשים. kodashim.
Okay, so this according he will pay though because if he doesn't
yeah I mean correct it gets to a little היזק שאינו ניכר
hezek she'eino nikkar case but we're already including היזק שאינו ניכר hezek
she'eino nikkar yes the כהן kohen does pay. אלא מוסר מאי טעמא?
ela moser mai ta'ama? Right, מוסר moser I'm sorry maybe I said
it wrong. Yes I was not suggesting because I think David's question
got me a little it was an excellent question but it got
me thinking in a different direction. Yes these cases I'm sorry if
I said it wrong, מוסר מפגל moser mefagel you definitely do pay.
Okay, I'm sorry I think I said it wrong, you definitely do
pay. The point of not being on the list is not to
suggest that you don't pay for them, it's just to say our
list is not all-inclusive, there are some things conceptually that we're not
dealing with. But yes you do pay, that's actually going to be
at the end at the tenth פרק perek in בבא קמא, Bava
Kamma, you inform on the government then you do pay, you're מפגל
mefagel you create פיגול pigul and you do pay. I'm sorry I
got a little distracted there. Okay, yes you do pay but it's
not on the list. Okay, so why is it not on the
list? So פיגול pigul is not on the list because we're not
dealing with קדשים. kodashim. אלא מוסר ela moser but when you hand
over you inform on somebody's property and you actually are going to
pay in that case מאי טעמא לא תני? mai ta'ama lo tani?
Why does he not include it in his list? Why conceptually is
it not in his list? So the גמרא Gemara says no שאני
מוסר דדיבורא, shani moser d'dibura, that's just words, ובדיבורא לא קא מיירי
u'vidibura lo ka mairi and we're not dealing with when you just
damage through words. Yes you are going to pay but it's just
through words. Actually you should say that's the biggest חידוש, chiddush, that's
the thing we should be talking about, that even in that case
you pay. But anyway we're not dealing with those cases. So the
גמרא Gemara says really? We're not dealing with words? Some of the
things were just words. So the
גמרא Gemara says והא מוציא שם רע? veha motzi shem ra? What
about the case of libel? דדיבורא הוא וקתני? de'dibura hu vekatni? That
was just words and that was listed. No דיבורא דאית ביה מעשה
הוא. dibura d'it bei ma'aseh hu. That's only words followed by an
act. It's only if he libels his wife, his bride after he's
had sex with her. But if he hasn't had sex and he
just libels her that actually that would not be in the פרשה
parsha in the תורה Torah because the פרשה parsha in the תורה
Torah is he comes and he says I had sex with my
wife and I discovered she wasn't a virgin and therefore I'm assuming
that she committed adultery. Okay, so actually if he just spread that
libel without having had sex he would not pay. So it's not
just words. Okay, the גמרא Gemara says והא עדים זוממים דדיבורא דלית
בהו מעשה הוא? veha edim zomemim d'dibura d'leit behu ma'aseh hu? How
about עדים זוממים? edim zomemim? They just give their testimony. Okay, so
we are talking about cases of damage with words וקתני? vekatni? and
it's listed? No התם אע"ג דלית ביה מעשה hatam af al gav
d'leit bei ma'aseh even though there is no act רחמנא קרייה מעשה
rachmana karyei ma'aseh the תורה Torah called it an act כדכתיב ועשיתם
לו כאשר זמם לעשות לאחיו, kedichtiv ve'asitem lo ka'asher zamam la'asot le'achiv,
you should do to them like they planned to do to their
brother. It's pretty funny. Actually it didn't call it an act. It
said they planned to do, it didn't say that they did to
their brother. But somehow because it's so to saying pay they should
get paid back for what they did or planned to do, it's
almost like considered the point is it's considered as if they did
it. Okay, so therefore but something that
if they actually did
do it it wouldn't be I know that's the irony. Anyway, if
something so even though this is like the biggest חידוש chiddush that
something could be pure words and you could pay for it, the
case of informing, right, nevertheless we didn't want to include it in
our
list. Maybe he's lying that they had sex. Right. And how do
we know—the related question you're going to ask is—and let's say, let's
say he says, "Wait, you can't make me pay because I was
only claiming to have had sex, but I really lied about it."
Would you have to actually—who would have the burden of proof? Yeah,
I don't know the answer to that, but it's a very good
question. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. So we've
got our list. Everybody agrees pretty much on every single case that
you pay. Maybe there's some debate whether you call something קנס knas
or ממון, mamon, but pretty much everybody agrees and there's just a
question of conceptually what's on your list or not on your list.
Okay? How—what type of list are you creating?
Was something true or something false?
We'll see about that.
I mean, you actually owe the money to the government, right?
So you're going to have to pay for your winnings. Very good.
So that's going to be a discussion in this פרק, perek, okay?
All these things are coming up. All right, so the גמרא Gemara
says, you see this opening סוגיא sugya is doing a very good
job. It's sort of whetting your appetite for a lot of the
things that are going to be discussed in the whole מסכת. masechet.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. So where the גמרא
Gemara
is...
Okay. Now we have to do with what the lists mean. What's
the point of having a list? בשלמא לתנא דידן תנא אבות מכלל
דאיכא תולדות. Bishlama l'tana didan tana avos mikhlal d'ika toldos. So for
our תנא, tana, אבות avos meant main categories to tell us that
there are—it's not just the cases in the תורה. Torah. Those are
abstract categories and there are things that are considered descendants or other
cases that are in those categories that have the same הלכה. halacha.
So the purpose of saying it's an אב av is to tell
you there are other types of things that also are called the
קרן keren and also are called the שן shen and also are
called the בור. bor. Okay? That's the point of calling them an
אב. av. אלא לרבי חייא ורבי אושעיא אבות מכלל דאיכא תולדות תולדותיהם
מאי ניהו? Ella l'Rabbi Chiya v'Rabbi Oshaya avos mikhlal d'ika toldos toldoseihem
mai nihu? Obviously for them, אבות avos does not mean that there
are categories and other things fall in it. What's the category of
מוציא שם רע? Motzi Shem Ra? What else falls into מוציא שם
רע? Motzi Shem Ra? What's the category of עדים זוממים? Eidim Zomemim?
There's just the thing itself. It's not abstracted and includes other things.
So why—what do you mean by calling them אבות? avos? What you
really mean is is that there are 24 scenarios of paying, but
why call them אבות? avos? What's the point? Well, okay, but what's
the point of having them all on the same list? So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבי אבהו כולן כאבות. Amar Rabbi Abbahu kulan
k'avos. They
are like the four classic אבות נזיקין, avos nezikin, okay, לשלם ממיטב,
l'shaleim m'meitav, that if you are going to pay from property and
not from land and not from cash and not from other types
of cattle, then you're going to have to pay from your best
land. מיטב שדהו ומיטב כרמו ישלם. Meitav sadeihu u'meitav karmo yeshaleim.
Now the—not even not from land?
No, no, not from cattle, not from cash, not from cattle. Did
I say it wrong? I don't think I did. I think anyway,
it doesn't matter. Okay? If you're going to pay from land, okay,
then you're going to pay from your best, but if you're going
to pay from cattle or from cash or whatever, then it's a
different story. But if you're going to pay from
land, it has to be your best. מיטב שדהו ומיטב כרמו ישלם.
Meitav sadeihu u'meitav karmo yeshaleim. Now in the תורה, Torah, that only
says it by ושלח את בעירו, v'shilach es be'iro, which we translate
to mean שן ורגל. shen v'regel. It doesn't say it by anything
else. But because of the four אבות נזיקין, avos nezikin, we're going
to think or assume are all linked to one another and therefore
it's going to be true by all the אבות, avos, by all
the four of our משנה, mishnah, by, you know, קרן שן רגל
בור ואש, keren shen regel bor v'eish, okay, all the ones in
our משנה. mishnah. Now by putting everything else on this list, okay,
including all of them, but by putting everything else on this list,
we are saying that any of these damages, any of these compensations,
whether it's שומרים, shomrim, whether it's גנב, gannav,
whether it's whatever, if you're paying from land, you're paying from the
best land. Now, how do we know that? So מאי טעמא? mai
ta'ama? Why, what's the reason for that? אתיא תחת תחת נתינה ישלם
כסף. Asya tachas tachas nesina yeshaleim kesef.
Okay? By all of the four classic אבות נזיקין, avos nezikin, it
uses either the word תחת, tachas, שלם ישלם שור תחת השור, shaleim
yeshaleim shor tachas hashor, okay, or ישלם, yeshaleim, I just gave you
an example, ישלם, yeshaleim, or נתינה, nesina, which is like כאשר—what's the
case of נתינה? nesina, Let's look at רש״י Rashi and כסף. kesef.
Let's look at רש״י. Rashi. תחת נתינה, tachas nesina, the first middle-sized
line in רש״י. Rashi.
שבכולן או תחת, Shebekulan o tachas, in all
the cases of the list we mentioned, כתיב או תחת, ksiv o
tachas, וגמרינן תחת תחת משור מועד דכתיב ביה
שור תחת השור. u'gamrinan tachas tachas mishor muad diksiv bei shor tachas
hashor. Okay? So שור תחת השור shor tachas hashor and we're again
assuming that any of the four אבות נזיקין avos nezikin is going
to be מיטב, meitav, דגמר משן ורגל דכתיב בהו מיטב
שדהו. degmar mishen v'regel diksiv behu meitav sadeihu. So שן ורגל shen
v'regel is the paradigm, מיטב שדהו, meitav sadeihu, and then it applies
to the other four. אף כאן מיטב. Af kan meitav. Okay? שאם
בא לשלם קרקע, She'im ba l'shaleim karka, if you're paying land, if
you pay cash or cattle it's different, but if you're paying land
לניזק משלם זה מן העידית, l'nizak m'shaleim zeh min ha'idis, the
best land. Okay? So either it says תחת, tachas, שור תחת השור,
shor tachas hashor, או נתינה. o nesina. Now, if it says נתינה,
nesina where does it say נתינה nesina by the four אבות נזיקין?
avos nezikin? וגמר נתינה נתינה משור שנגח את העבד דכתיב ביה. Vegamar
nesina nesina mishor shenagach es ha'eved diksiv bei. כסף שלשים שקלים יתן
לאדוניו. kesef shloshim shekalim yitein l'adonav. So
it says נתינה nesina, by one of the cases of the אבות
נזיקין. avos nezikin. או ישלם, o yishalem, where does it say ישלם?
yishalem? שן ורגל, shein v'regel, דכתיב מיטב שדהו ישלם. d'chtiv meitav sadeihu
yishalem.
Okay, that's the best one. Okay, או כסף, o kesef, וגם היא
מיבעי דכתיב ביה כסף ישיב
לבעליו. v'gam hi mibei d'chtiv bei kesef yashiv l'ba'alav.
So in all of the four אבות נזיקין, avos nezikin, you either
have the word כסף, kesef, ישלם, yishalem, נתינה, nesina, or תחת. tachat.
And by one of them, by שן ורגל shein v'regel it says
you pay from the best land, so then we link and say
all the אבות נזיקין avos nezikin you pay from the best land,
and now we're going to now say that so and now we're
going to say
everything
else on this list has one of those key words in it,
תחת, tachat, נתינה, ישלם, yishalem, כסף, kesef, one of the words that
appears in the אבות נזיקין, avos nezikin, and therefore they also are
going to pay from the best land. If you want to know
where those words appear, you can read the rest of the רש״י
Rashi for yourself. Okay, so there are four main so the
first step of אבות avos is you take the concrete cases in
the תורה Torah of a well and of a fire and of
an ox and you say it's not just a physical well, it's
a conceptual category, it's abstracted, it's an
אב av and there are תולדות. toldos. But there's another point, that
those four, because they're linked to one another, they're like the case
of שן ורגל shein v'regel and if you're paying land you pay
the best land and now רבי אושעיא ורבי חייא Rabbi Oshaya v'Rabbi
Chiya say let me give you a full list of all types
of damages, of compensatory damages. What's the point, who needs a list?
The list is to tell you all of these because they have
one of those key words in them are going to also pay
from the best land. It's also just convenient to put all the
types of different ממונות mamonos together and compensation together, you know, just
to organize information, but the גמרא Gemara wants to understand that there's
some halachic significance of I guess the point the גמרא Gemara is
saying is not just why did it use the word אבות, avos,
why not just say there are twenty-four payments of ממון. mamon. So
not just a list you want because you want to organize you
know your information, you want to just pull together what are all
the different types of ways you can pay, but the use of
calling them אבות avos is to tell you they're like the classic
four אבות avos that they will pay from the best land. Okay,
now we move on in the משנה. Mishnah. We got פשט pshat
in the משנה, Mishnah, we've got other types of lists, moving on
in the משנה. Mishnah. לא הרי השור כהרי המבעה. lo ha-rei ha-shor
k'harei ha-mav'eh. So a שור shor is not like מבעה, mav'eh, we've
already explained what that means, either it's שן ורגל shein v'regel or
אדם ושור adam v'shor and but they both have in common is
that they are they are they are living, they are רוח חיים.
ruach chayim. מאי קאמר? mai ka'amar?
So what's the point of this saying ולא הרי, v'lo ha-rei, what's
the משנה Mishnah doing? So אמר זביד משמיה דרבא הכי קאמר, amar
Zevid mishmeih d'Rava hachi ka'amar, this is what the משנה Mishnah is
doing. ליכתוב רחמנא חדא, lichtov rachmana chada, why just give me one
of the four אבות, avos, right? Why do I need all four?
ותיתי אידך מינה, v'tisei idach minah, and let me derive the other
ones from one case. Okay, הדר אמר חדא מחדא לא אתיא. hadar
amar chada m'chada lo asya. So the משנה Mishnah is telling you
this, you can't learn the others out, each one has something distinct.
שור, shor, you know, שן shein has something that רגל regel doesn't
have, רגל regel has something שן shein doesn't have. Let's learn out
from two of them. Oh no, because they both have something everything
else don't have, they're both alive, other things aren't alive. So the
point of the משנה Mishnah is to tell me you couldn't have
learned it out from just one or two of them. ולא זה
וזה שיש בהן רוח חיים. v'lo zeh v'zeh she-yeish bahen ruach chayim.
מאי קאמר? mai ka'amar? Tell me how do you read this next
line? אמר משרשיא משמיה דרבא הכי קאמר. amar Mesharshaya mishmeih d'Rava hachi
ka'amar. This is what the next line is saying. ליכתוב lichtov oh
you see I didn't know we were going to get through with
a דף daf today. Okay, ליכתוב רחמנא תרתי ותיתי אידך מינייהו. lichtov
rachmana tarti v'tisei idach mineihu.
Just write two of them. So you can't learn everything out from
שן shein because שן shein has הנאה. hana'ah. You can't learn it
out from רגל regel because רגל regel is הזיקו מצוי. hezeiko matzui.
You can't learn it out from the two of them combined, learn
it out from the common denominator. Nope, you can't learn it out
from the common denominator because they are both רוח חיים. ruach chayim.
Okay, learn it out from three. Learn it out from them and
אש. eish. No, you can't learn out from three because they all
go and damage and בור bor stays in its place. So the
whole point is to point out you needed all of them, you
couldn't have learned it out from just one or two or three.
Okay, now the problem is is that if you really think about
it, you can learn it out from fewer because that's what רבא
Rava is going to say. So הדר אמר חדא מתרתי לא אתיא.
hadar amar chada mi-tarti lo asya. Then it says you can't even
learn one from two. אמר רבא, amar Rava, but really לכולהו, l'chul'hu,
if any of them, דשדית בור בינייהו אתו כולהו במה הצד. d'shadisa
bor beineihu asu chul'hu b'ma hatzad. If you did בור bor plus
any one of the other ones, then you really could include everything.
לבר מקרן. l'var mi-keren. The one thing you couldn't include is קרן
keren משום דאיכא למיפרך מה לכולהו שכן מועדים מתחלתן. mi-shum d'ika l'mifrach
mah l'chul'hu she-kein mu'adin mitichlatan.
Except for קרן keren because קרן keren is weaker than all of
them because all everything else has a propensity to damage and you
pay full damages at the outset. קרן keren does not have a
propensity to damage. What does רבא Rava mean? Okay, because the way
the משנה Mishnah was structured, right, is it says like this, right?
שור shor and מבעה mav'eh
are רוח חיים. ruach chayim. Okay, again whether this is אדם adam
or שן ורגל, shein v'regel, these are live things. Okay, so you
couldn't necessarily say that you have to pay when the thing that
does the damage is not live. Add to it אש. eish. Okay,
so now let me learn from all of this that you can
pay. No, because what all of these have is דרכן לילך ולהזיק,
darkan leilech u'l'hazik, right? So you can't apply it to something like
a בור bor that doesn't
go. Great, but you’re telling me that בור bor is at the
bottom of the list. So this is the weakest thing because this
doesn’t even go out and damage. You come to it. So just
learn everything else from בור. bor. You can't- sure you couldn't have
learned it out from these things. These are more liable, make more
sense. But learn it out from the thing that makes the least
sense to be liable for. Ah, but what you can't learn- but
the reason you can't just say if it tells me בור bor
I can figure out everything else is בור bor has one thing
that makes it very, you know, very liable for damage, which is
what? It is תחילת עשייתו לנזק. techilat asiyato lenezek. What?
I think in some ways it's it's even more default. Right.
תחילת עשייתו לנזק, techilat asiyato lenezek, meaning it is its whole creation,
it begins its life as a hazard. Okay, there's another thing as
well which the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to say which is also מעשיו
גרמו לו. ma'asav garmo lo. You directly made the בור, bor, okay?
These other things you didn't make. Oh, you made the fire, but
the fire then traveled further. Anyway, okay, but it's תחילת עשייתו לנזק.
techilat asiyato lenezek. So therefore you can't learn everything from בור bor
because these other things don't aren't created as as hazards. But what
רבא Rava is saying is, okay, but learn it out from בור
bor plus one other thing. Okay? So then I would say, look,
if you're חייב chayav by בור bor which doesn't go out and
damage, you should certainly be חייב chayav by everything else which goes
out and damage. Ah, but maybe you're חייב chayav by בור bor
because it starts its its beginning of its existence as a hazard.
Oh, but a שור'ס shor's beginning of existence isn't a hazard, a
fire's beginning of existence, you might say it's a little bit but
not the same as a בור bor kind of in the middle
of רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, okay? So these other things don't start
life as a hazard, so you don't it's so you don't need
the fact that you start life as a hazard because that's not
true about this. You don't need the fact that they go out
and damage because that's not true about בור. bor. So if I
eliminate the distinct characteristic, I then have the abstraction which applies to
any type of a thing that I have a an obligation to
watch. So רבא Rava says you could really learn out everything from
בור bor plus one of them, you didn't need all four categories.
Now what you could not learn out was קרן, keren, was goring.
Why couldn't you learn out goring? Because goring, well, no meaning if
it had not-
because he said it has the damage-
no, no but we wouldn't have known it was half damage. We
would- oh you could say we wouldn't have known half damage. But
if the תורה Torah had never said goring, I would have said,
sure you're חייב chayav by בור bor and אש eish and שן
shein and רגל regel because those are things that an animal will
naturally do. We you know are natural types of things to expect.
But normal animals don't go out and gore, so maybe I should
be exempt, fully exempt, I won't even pay half. Okay? I would
never have known that you paid when an animal goes out and
gores because that is not its natural propensity to do that. It
has a potential... it has a- yes, but nevertheless if the תורה
Torah told me you're חייב chayav by בור bor and אש eish
and שן shein and רגל, regel, I would have said the תורה
Torah maybe based- if my if something
completely unexpected, my animal goes and gores, maybe I should be fully
exempt, right? Why would I think I would pay half? Maybe I
could say if it did it three times I could figure out
that I should be חייב, chayav, but the first three times I
would logically say it's completely unexpected, I should be fully exempt. So
the one thing you couldn't have learned out was קרן. keren. So
basically at the end of the day what רבא Rava is saying
is, is that you needed is that you needed three. You needed
בור bor plus one to learn out you know to learn out
the other to learn out everything else and you needed קרן keren
because קרן keren anyway you couldn't learn out by itself. Okay?
But כי שדית בור בינייהו, ki shaddit bor beineiyhu, if you add
בור bor amongst them, אתיא כלהו במה הצד, atya kulhu b'ma hatzad,
you learn everything out by a common denominator לבד מקרן. levad m'keren.
The one thing you couldn't have learned out is if it was
שור shor and קרן- keren it was it was בור bor and
קרן keren by the way, right? Then you could have- like because
here you've got let's say just to put them all up there.
קרן, Keren, שן, shein, רגל, regel, and אדם. adam. Okay? So if
it was בור bor and קרן, keren, then you could have learned
everything out. If you're going to pay קרן keren even though it
doesn't have a propensity, you should certainly pay everything else that has
a propensity. Okay? Ah, but every- you know, but maybe I wouldn't
have included בור bor because that's stationary. Oh, but if you pay
for so you know so that's why I have to say בור,
bor, you know? But it's not but that's תחילת עשייתו לנזק. techilat
asiyato lenezek. Okay so that's- anyway fine. If it was קרן keren
and בור bor you could have learned out everything, okay? That even
though you know that you don't need תחילת עשייתו לנזק, techilat asiyato
lenezek, you know, you don't need כוונתו להזיק, kavanato lehazik, and even
something that's it's not doesn't have a propensity to do. But if
it was בור bor plus one of these, you would have learned
out most of them but you still would have needed קרן. keren.
Okay, but you certainly don't need everything is what רבא Rava is
saying. Alright? So if you have שור shor plus בור bor plus
one, if the one you could learn out everything but קרן keren
and בור bor plus קרן keren is everything.
Okay now it's
starting to get complicated and that's why you need רש"י. Rashi. Fine,
but anyway that's why we have this big רש"י Rashi because רש"י
Rashi works through all the all the combinations, okay? But בור bor
plus one is everything but קרן. keren. בור bor plus קרן keren
is everything. Okay now, he says like this: ולמאן דאמר אדרבה קרן
עדיפא שכוונתו להזיק, U'le-man d'amar adiraba keren adifa she-kavanato lehazik, and according
to the one that says actually קרן keren is certainly going to
be liable, even though it doesn't have a propensity... to do it
because it intentionally
damages, אפילו קרן נמי אתי afilu keren nami atie you could even
learn out קרן. keren. Now who is this מאן דאמר, mand amar,
who is the one that says that even though קרן keren doesn't
have a propensity to do it and nevertheless the fact that it's
doing it intentionally clearly makes it more חמור? chamur? Like who is
it exactly that
weighs it in a way, it means you pay נזק שלם?
nezek shalem? It's more obvious, well yes, and it's more obvious you
would pay. But who is the one that makes it like calculus?
It says like clearly you put the two together, it doesn't have
a propensity but כוונתו להזיק, kavanaso lehazik, כוונתו להזיק kavanaso lehazik wins
out and it's more חמור chamur and you could have learned it
out. So who is this person that says this? So Rashi says
the last of the medium sized lines of Rashi ולמאן דאמר לא
איתפרש היכא, uleman de'amar lo isparesh heicha,
it was never explained who this person is, who this opinion is.
Tosafot says I'll tell you who this person is because here's who
it is. It's you, no, it is, it is a very important
debate that we are going to come up with in about ten
days about why do you pay half damages by קרן. keren. Are
סתם שור בחזקת שימור stam shor bechezkas shimur or סתם שור לאו
בחזקת שימור, stam shor lav bechezkas shimur, meaning what we've been saying
that a קרן keren does not—an animal does not have a propensity
to gore—is that really true? Okay, do you say that fundamentally
animals do not have a propensity to gore? And if it gores
you're really an אונס oness and you really should pay zero. But
you know what, you could have gone the extra mile. You know,
it's like
if you were to draw a line, what's the likelihood that it'll
gore, it just
is—it's just under the line of minimum care—minimum care that you should
be doing. So technically you didn't have to watch it and technically
you should be paying zero. But we want you to be a
little bit more vigilant and therefore we're going to make you pay
half. And that would understand that the half payment by קרן keren
is a קנס knass because technically you should be paying nothing. The
other way to say it is the exact opposite. It's just over
the line. Actually, in terms of minimum care that you need, there's
just enough likelihood that an animal might gore that you should be
doing that. So technically speaking, you should be paying full. But it
is so close to that line that we're going to go easy
on you the first three times and make you pay half. According
to that, the payment of קרן keren is ממון mamon not קנס.
knass. That's going to be a debate later on. So Tosafot says
that's what's going on here. If I hadn't known קרן keren I
would have paid, okay? It's only true if I say that קרן
keren fundamentally is below the line, does not have a propensity to
gore. But if I say technically קרן keren is just above the
line, then I even if it had not been written I would
have made you pay. Actually, I would have made you pay full.
Okay, as the חידוש chidush of the Torah is that you don't
pay full, you pay half according to that way of thinking about
it. But that's what he says, קרן עדיפא keren adifa not only
because כוונתו להזיק, kavanaso lehazik, but that your assumption that it doesn't
have a likelihood to gore is actually wrong. Technically it has enough
of a likelihood that you should be paying. Yes?
So the קנס knass approach to that because you're—you're imposing a fine
on somebody who you think wasn't negligent in some way.
No, wasn't as vigilant as they should have been, right.
Whereas this other ממון, mamon,
you're doing it on the back of the guy who got damaged.
Right, I understand. Like why should I lose out just because, you
know, the Torah wants to go easy on you? Well you know,
I don't have a full answer except that it's two ways of
saying, two ways of saying it's a borderline case, okay? What it's
really saying, if you want another word like this, are you negligent
or not, this is exactly a borderline case so we're going to
split it. Okay, and then the only question is, okay, but conceptually
which way would you lean on that to define it as קנס
knass or as ממון? mamon? I understand what you're saying because—but I'm
trying to say it's not—like if you say it's clearly over the
line, then why should the other guy suffer? But if we all
can agree it's a borderline case, right, then you sort of understand—understand
it. But at the end of the day we have to categorize
it as קנס knass or as ממון. mamon. Anyway, we'll get more
time to discuss that in about ten days. It's coming up at
the end of the פרק. perek. Now, anyway, so למאן דאמר קרן
עדיפא, leman de'amar keren adifa, so reading this like Tosafot, according to
the approach that קרן keren is actually the strongest thing to be
liable for because כוונתו להזיק kavanaso lehazik because it's intending to damage
and because, as I just explained,
technically speaking it's over the line and you really do have—and it
really does have a propensity enough that you're negligent. אפילו קרן נמי
אתי, afilu keren nami atie, you could have learned out everything! בור
bor plus any one, you would have gotten everything.
Okay, צד השוה שבהן שדרכן להזיק ושמירתן עליך. tzad hashaveh shebahen shedarkan
lehazik ushmirasan alecha. So if that's true, ואלא מאי הלכתא כתבינהו רחמנא?
ve'ela mai hilchesa kesvino rachmana? So why does the Torah have to
give me four categories? Give me two categories.
להלכותיהן, lehilchosehen,
to tell you because each category has special הלכות. halachos. It's not
just a big generic anything you should be watching if it damages
you're liable for payment. By putting it in one of the four
categories, some distinctive הלכות halachos apply to each case. What are the
distinctive הלכות? halachos? קרן לחלק בין תם למועד. keren lechalek bein tam
lemuad. קרן keren we just said that the first three times you
pay half, afterwards you pay full, so it's important to know if
you put something. to the קרן Keren category. שן ורגל, shein ve'regel,
the eating and the trampling, the פטור ברשות הרבים patur b'reshus harabbim
to exempt you in the public domain, we discussed that yesterday because
they are either just because of public policy we have to let
people have their animals in the public domain, or because the פחת
הניזק, p'chas hanizek, the fact that you leave yourself exposed in רשות
הרבים reshus harabbim when you know there are going to be animals
means that you are contributory negligent, but it's important to know that
there's that idea and that if you put something in a שן
ורגל shein ve'regel category, you'll be exempt in the public domain. בור,
Bor, a well, לפטור בו את הכלים, liftur bo es hakelim, that's
going to be a that's a that's going to be a strange
one, we'll talk about that, but we understand later that if my
vessels break in the well, my camel falls down and he has
vessels on its back, that the that the, you know, that the
pots and pans or whatever break, that actually you don't have to
pay. ולרבי יהודה דמחייב על נזקי כלים בבור, u'le-Rabbi Yehuda d'mechayev al
nizkei kelim b'bor, according to Rabbi Yehuda that says you pay for
when vessels get damaged, לפטור בו את האדם, liftur bo es ha-adam,
if a person not gets injured but dies in the well, you're
exempt. So there are exemptions for the case of the well. אדם,
Adam, why does the Torah say a person pays when he damages
something else? לחייבו בארבעה דברים, lechayvo be'arba'ah devarim, to tell you cases
of personal injury, that if he actually damages not property but another
person, there's going to be all those additional payments. אש, Eish, how
about fire? Why did that have to be written? לפטור בו את
הטמון, liftur bo es hatamun, because we're going to find out later
that if the fire burns down a haystack and there's something buried
in the haystack, the classic needle, right, anyway, you're exempt on things
that were buried, only on things that are exposed.
Okay, so this means things buried underground,
like if No, it could also mean that. ולרבי יהודה דמחייב על
נזקי טמון באש, u'le-Rabbi Yehuda d'mechayev al nizkei tamun b'eish, and about
Rabbi Yehuda that says you're חייב chayav for things that are buried,
for things that are not exposed, so what what what does it
mean to put something in the אש eish category? לאתויי מאי? le'asuyei
mai? So what are you including, meaning what's the purpose of the
אש eish category?
לאתויי ללחכה נירו וסכסכה אבניו. le'asuyei lichacha niro vesichacha avanav. If the
fire let's say burns stones or burns like the surface of the
ground, so it doesn't destroy something, it's not like something burns up.
Right, you had your hay and now you don't have your hay.
It blacks and it... it chars something, okay, and Rashi says it's
not like a classic type of a thing that fire does, okay,
or whatever, but it doesn't really fully consume it, so it so
to tell you that in that case actually you are going to
be exempt. You're only חייב, chayav, minute,
no I'm sorry, you are חייב, chayav, excuse me, the same, you
are חייב, chayav, excuse me, שלחכה אש חרישות חבירו וסכסכה אבניו חייב
באבנים, she'lichacha eish charishos chaveiro vesichacha avanav chayav b'avanin, חייב, chayav, right,
so you might have thought, right,
I'm sorry, right, you might have thought, one minute, right, you might
have thought that you are not חייב chayav because that is not
as things you should have expected or it's not a normal I
know, I don't exactly get why I would have thought it's not
חייב, chayav, but... What? But you said
Yeah, I don't know.
Yeah, Rashi calls it
לחייבו בהני דלאו מאורחא דמתניתין המוצא לחייב בדבר שאינו ראוי לו שאין
עיקר אש בכך. lechayvo bahanei d'lav me-orsa d'masnisan, hamotzei lechayiv b'davar she'eino
rauy lo, she'ein ikar eish be-kach. That's not the classic fire. I
don't understand, it's a classic damage of fire, I mean fire is
normally made to consume fuel and not to char things. I don't
really get why that's such a חידוש, chiddush, but the חידוש chiddush
of אש eish is that you're חייב chayav even in that case.
Now what we're going to pick up tomorrow is, okay, you've got
four categories and each one has its special laws, and now you've
got this big catch-all abstract category. Okay, what happens when you can't
fit something neatly into one of the four? Does it get caught
by this big abstract category, and if so, which of the laws
do you apply to it? Right? How do you deal with the
fact that you both have four distinct categories, each one with its
distinct laws, and you have one big, you know, umbrella abstract category?
So what are the unique laws that apply to that?
So what are your big what's the abstract?
כל שדרכו להזיק ושמירתן עליך חב המזיק לשלם. kol she-darko le'hazik u'shemirasan
alecha chav hamazik leshaleim. So if I have something that's not exactly
אש eish and not exactly בור, bor, not exactly שור, shor, but
I include it because of צד השוה, tzad hashaveh, because it's my
property and I have a responsibility to watch it, so what laws
apply to it? Am I חייב ברשות הרבים? chayav b'reshus harabbim? Am
I do I pay half? Right? You know, what are the special
which of the laws apply to it when you have this big
abstract category as well? So that's what we're going to continue with
with tomorrow is looking at that broader category now that we've identified
four concrete ones and the fact that combined they give you some
big abstract rule. Okay, to be continued tomorrow.